<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC0793 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.0793.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC1738 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1738.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC1950 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1950.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2119 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2285 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2285.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2616 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2616.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2617 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2617.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2629 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC2818 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2818.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC4366 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4366.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC4559 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4559.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC5246 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6454 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6454.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC6455 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6455.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7230 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7230.xml'>
  <!ENTITY RFC7231 PUBLIC '' 'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7231.xml'>
  ]>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xml"?>

<?rfc toc="yes" symrefs="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="info" docName="draft-montenegro-httpbis-h2ot-latest">
  <front>
	  <title abbrev="HTTP/2 for IoT">HTTP/2 for the Internet of Things</title>

    <author initials="G." surname="Montenegro" fullname="Gabriel Montenegro">
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <email>Gabriel.Montenegro@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="July" year="2015" />
    <area>Applications</area>
    <keyword>HTTP, IoT</keyword>
    <abstract>
	    <t>
This document makes the case for HTTP/2 for IoT. 
	    </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
	<t>
    When the IETF started work on IoT with the 6lowpan WG, it was clear that in addition to the lower-layer adaptation work 
    for IPv6, much work elsewhere in the stack was necessary. One of the main questions was what protocol to use for 
    applications in IoT. That question may not have a single answer that is always best for all scenarios and use
    cases. There are many such use cases, in accordance with the fact that "IoT" means too many things.
    
</t>
<t> 
    Accordingly, the IoT landscape includes a proliferation of options for any particular functionality 
    (protocols, encoding, security suites, authentication/authorization, etc). 
    Many of these are being created expressly for IoT (within the IETF and elsewhere) with the 
    justification that the mainstream options could not possibly be usable for IoT scenarios, 
    leading towards multiple disparate networking and software stacks. This adds complexity to IoT 
    and, importantly, amplifies the attack surface. However, properly configured and implemented, 
    mainstream options may not just be workable, but may even be the best option. 
</t>
<t> 
    In terms of transport, HTTP/2 is now widely available. Moreover the ongoing effort to layer HTTP/2 
    over UDP (i.e., over QUIC) adds a useful capability for IoT. We show the current suitability of 
    HTTP/2 for IoT scenarios and examine possible improvements.    
    </t>
    <t>
    Let's look at some application communication patterns to establish some
    common language:
    
   <list style='hanging'>
		<t hangText="node to node:"> 
			A constrained node engages in direct communication with another constrained node.
		</t>
    
		<t hangText="node to gateway:"> 
			A constrained node and a gateway node engage in direct communication. A gateway node is directly on both a constrained network
      (e.g., a lowpan) and on a non-constrained network (a normal network using mainstream stack implementations, typically connected 
      to the Internet).
		</t>
    
		<t hangText="gateway to cloud:">
			A gateway node (see above) engages in communication with unconstrained networks, typically a cloud service on the Internet.
		</t>

		<t hangText="gateway to cloud:">			
      A node on a constrained network engages in direct communcation with unconstrained networks, typically a cloud service on the Internet.
		</t>
	</list>   
	</t>

	<t>
    We can further categorize the above communication patterns into two basic types of networking exchanges:

   <list style='hanging'>
		<t hangText="Constrained network scenario:"> 
			A constrained network scenario includes node to node and node to gateway exchanges.
		</t>
    
		<t hangText="Internet scenario:"> 
			An Internet scenario includes gateway to cloud and node to cloud exchanges.
		</t>
	</list> 
	</t>
  
	<t>
    This document makes the case for HTTP/2 as the most general protocol of choice for Internet of Things applications,
    suitable for both Constrained network scenarios and Internet scenarios.
	</t>
	</section>


<section title="Application Transport Alternatives and their Strengths"> 
  <t>
		A recent survey by the Eclipse IoT working group queried IoT developers about the protocols and technologies they are using 
    and planning to use. Some of the 
    currently used application transport protocols (above the link layer) for IoT applications are as follows:
    
  <list style='symbols'>
		<t> 
			HTTP/1.1 (63% of developers)
		</t>
		<t> 
			MQTT (53% of developers)
		</t>
		<t> 
			CoAP (21% of developers)
		</t>
		<t> 
			Others: AMQP and XMPP (11% of developers)
		</t>
	</list>
  
	</t>
  
  <t>
    The sections below provide some more details.
  </t>   
  
    <section title="HTTP/1.1"> 
		<t> 
      HTTP/1.1 is a text-based protocol, and is widely successful as it is the basis not just for the web, but for much non-web traffic in the internet today.
      Most (but not all) of the instances of HTTP today version 1.1 as specified in RFC2616. Since its publication back in 1999 it has evolved organically,
      producing countless variations and exceptions to its rules. Modern browser and server implementations have very complex and convoluted
      code to deal with parsing and handling the many nuances of the protocol. Because of all this confusion, the HTTPbis working group set out to
      clarify the existing specifications, and after a multi-year effort to clarify its many sources of confusion, it has published a cleaner specification
      in RFCs 7230-7235. In spite of this, the protocol still has a plethora of legacy issues and remains too verbose.
		</t>

		<t>       
      HTTP/1.1 is very clearly a mismatch for the constrained devices and networks that characterize IoT. Despite its shortcomings, it is the most 
      popular protocol for IoT applications (63% per the aforementioned survey). Why would such an ill-suited protocol be clearly the most
      popular for IoT applications? It is by far the most commonly known protocol. It has
      many implementations, plenty in open source, with massive support in all platforms, tools and APIs. It is easy to find know-how and support. 
      In short, it has the power and convenience that comes with being the mainstream protocol. 
		</t>
    
		<t>       
      Another major advantage is that it is the protocol that has the best chance of traversing firewalls and middle boxes in the internet due 
      to its use of port 80 when in the clear, and, especially, its use of port 443 when over TLS.
		</t>    
    </section>

    <section title="MQTT"> 
		<t> 
      MQ Telemetry Transport (MQTT) is a publish/subscribe messaging protocol created by IBM, now being standardized
      by OASIS. It is popular in the internet scenario (node to cloud, gateway to cloud). It is a compact, binary protocol,
      and is very popular in certain application domains.
		</t>

		<t>       
      It is the second most popular protocol in the survey (behind HTTP/1.1) with 53% of developers using it. In the internet scenario,
      however, TLS is mandatory. In practice, additional TLS overhead is required for all Internet scenario exchanges, so all
      protocols are slightly larger and MQTT loses some relative size advantage. There is a spec for MQTT over UDP, but, by far 
      it is most commonly deployed over TCP (port 8833 when over TLS,
      port 1883 without TLS). Even when using TLS, it has the well-known firewall traversal issues common to any protocol not over port 
      443.
		</t>
    </section>

    <section title="CoAP"> 
		<t> 
      CoAP is a compact, binary UDP-based protocol based on RESTful principles and closely patterned after HTTP/1.1. 
      It also adds some semantics.  
		</t>
   	<t> 
      When the IETF CoAP 
		</t>

		<t>       

		</t>
    </section>

</section>



    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
    Thanks for interesting discussions to Ivan Pashov, Robby Simpson and Geoff Mulligan.
      </t>
      <t>
    This document was produced using the xml2rfc tool <xref target="RFC2629"/>. 
      </t>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC2119;
      &RFC2616;
      &RFC7230;
      &RFC7231;
   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC2629;
   </references>
  </back>
</rfc>

<!--
  edited with Visual Studio Code
  -->